Harry Norman Gardiner papers, 1855 - 1927 (bulk 1870 - 1930)
Smith College Archives
Harry Norman Gardiner papers
1855 - 1927
1870 - 1930
Gardiner, H. Norman (Harry Norman), 1855-1927
42 UUID:233a789c-36e7-45ad-b5f6-5612b413023a
20 boxes (7.75 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Faculty. Contains correspondence, lecture notes and publications, and correspondence.
Harry Norman Gardiner was born on November 6, 1855 in Norwich, England. He received his primary education in Bristol and spent four years as a businessman in England before emigrating to the United States in 1874 with the hopes of becoming a minister. He graduated from Amherst College in 1878 with high honors and immediately entered Union Theological Seminary in New York. After graduating in 1881, his outstanding success and dedication to his studies earned him a fellowship in Europe. Two years later, he returned to Amherst College to pursue a Master of Art (1885).
Gardiner joined the Smith College faculty in 1884 as an instructor in mental and moral philosophy. During his career he became well known both in Northampton and in the philosophical and psychological academic community. Gardiner was the first secretary of the American Philosophical Association and became president of the organization in 1907. He was a charter member of the American Psychological Association and an advisory editor of the Psychological Review, a journal to which he frequently contributed. He also published in the Psychological Bulletin, Encyclopedia Americana, and Encyclopedia Britannica. His book titled Outlines in Modern Philosophy was published in 1892.
Gardiner was a member of the Century Club of New York, the Amherst College Club of New York, served as the vice-president and as trustee for the Nonotuck Savings Bank of Northampton and as a deacon at the First Church of Northampton. When Gardiner retired from Smith College in 1924, he had taught there for forty years and served as department chairman. Upon his retirement, Gardiner became the first man to be awarded an honorary doctor of humane letters from Smith College. In 1926, one of the new dormitories in the quadrangle was named the Harry N. Gardiner House. Extremely proud of this honor, he would often bring guests to "his house" for dinner.
After his retirement, Gardiner still remained close to Smith and the surrounding community. He sometimes led morning chapel and looked forward to the opportunity to substitute teach a philosophy class. President William Allen Neilson and Gardiner collaborated upon a history of the college with the working title Smith College: the First Seventy Years. Although Neilson continued working on the manuscript after Gardiner's death, it was never completed.
On December 29, 1927 Gardiner had just finished a late afternoon tea date with President Neilson and was walking home to his Main Street apartment when he was struck by a oncoming automobile. A cracked skull caused the instant death of the seventy-two year old. He willed Smith College he willed his books and manuscripts on psychology and philosophy, his portraits of philosophers, and a Spanish crucifix. He was survived by his niece, Mrs. Hilda (Edwards) Hamlin (Class of 1912), who was his only living relative.
The collection contains the professional papers of Harry Norman Gardiner, Smith College Professor of Philosophy. The papers are arranged in eight series and contain clippings, correspondence, curricular materials, photographs and speeches.
This collection is organized into eight series:
Biographical Material
Correspondence
Lecture Notes
Notes
Photographs
Publications
Speeches
Writings
Index to Autograph Album
Prepared by Madison White, Class of 2016. Names retain original order as found within the album. Under the the heading 'Type', autographed letter signed is abbreviated by "ALS".
James, William 3 ALS 1890, 1895
Davidson, Thomas 1 ALS 1894
Morgan, Conway Lloyd 1 ALS 1896
Harris, William Torrey 1 ALS 1894
Dewey, John 1 ALS 1895
Hall, Granville Stanley 1 ALS 1892
Muensterberg, Hugo 1 ALS 1895
Knight, William Angus 1 ALS 1898
Seth, James 1 ALS 1905
Delabarre, Edmund Burke ALS (portion) undated
Marshall, Henry Rutgers 1 ALS undated
Creighton, James Edwin 1 ALS 1899
Hibben, John Grier 1 ALS 1901
Ladd, George Trumbull 1 ALS 1904
Woodbridge, Fredrick autograph undated
Santayana, George 1 ALS 1903
Adler, Felix autograph undated
Puffer, Ethel Dench autograph undated
Talbot, Ellen Bliss autograph undated
Lutoslawski, Wincenty 1 ALS 1907
Judd, Charles Hubbard autograph undated
Forbes, George Mather autograph undated
Gruber, Abraham 1 ALS undated
Evans, Daniel autograph undated
Sheldon, Wilmon Henry autograph undated
Bakewell, Charles M. autograph undated
Cohen, Morris R. 1 ALS 1912
Euken, Rudolf 1 ALS 1912
Hoernle, R.F. Alfred 1 ALS 1913
Warren, Howard Crosby autograph undated
Russell, Bertrand 1 ALS 1914
Goodell, Thomas Dwight 1 ALS 1919
deWulf, Maurice 1 ALS circa 1915
Calkins, Mary Whiton 1 ALS 1908
Overstreet, Harry Allen autograph undated
Jones, Henry 1 ALS 1918
Pankhurst, Helen Hess autograph 1919
More, Paul Elmer autograph undated
Jastrow, Joseph autograph 1919
Barker, Ernest autograph 1920
McDougall, William autograph 1921
Everett, Walter Goodnow autograph 1923
Dickinson, S. Miller autograph 1924
Carritt, G.F. 1 ALS undated
Jacks, L.P. autograph 1924
Salter, William S. autograph 1925
Radhakrishnan, S. autograph 1926
Landis, A.D. 1 ALS 1928
various attendees, Meeting of the American Philosophical Association (Smith College) various 12/28/1925
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The Harry Norman Gardiner papers were donated to the College Archives.
Gardiner, H. Norman (Harry Norman), 1855-1927; Smith College -- Faculty -- History -- Sources.; Smith College -- Student housing; Smith College. Department of Philosophy.; scrapbooks
- Biographical Material
  Contains newspaper clippings, memorial tributes, honorary degrees, class notes, biographical sketch.
- Correspondence
  Contains correspondence between friends, family and philosophers. Also a collection of correspondence of Henry Rutgers Marshall to and from eminent philosophers of the day.
- Lecture Notes
  Contains notes for classes taught at Smith College.
- Notes
  Notes on books, articles and other subjects.
- Photographs
  Various photographs, 1885 - 1927.
- Publications
  Contains articles, books, and translations, published and unpublished.
- Speeches
  Contains manuscripts, notes, and typescripts of talks given outside of college classes.
- Writings
  Contains papers written for various occasions, not intended for publication.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - general undated (Box 809, Folder 1)
  - inventory undated (Box 809, Folder 2)
  - "Biographical Sketch", written by Hilda Edwards Hamlin 1912 (Box 809, Folder 3)
  - death - correspondence 1927 (Box 809, Folder 4)
  - death - memorial service 1927 (Box 809, Folder 5)
  - England 1870 (Box 809, Folder 6)
  - Honorary Degree, Smith College 1927 (Box 809, Folder 7)
  - Union Theological Seminary - "Memorial Tablet in Honor of Dr. Gardiner" 1928 - 1930 (Box 810, Folder 8)
  - Union Theological Seminary, "Church History" with Dr. Hitchcock 1881 - 1882 (Box 810, Folder 1)
  - Union Theological Seminary, "Biblical Theology" with Dr. Briggs 1881 (Box 810, Folder 2)
  - Union Theological Seminary, "Systematic Theology" with Dr. Shedd 1880 - 1881 (Box 810, Folder 3)
  - Union Theological Seminary, "Systematic Theology" with Dr. Shedd Dogmatic Theology" undated (Box 810, Folder 4)
  - Amherst College, "Titus Lucretius Carus: Poet and Philosopher" 1878 (Box 811, Folder 1)
  - University of Berlin, "Neu testament Theoloogie in systemischer Form" with Dr. B. Weiss 1880 (Box 811, Folder 2)
  - University of Leipzig, "Psychologie" with Wilhelm Wundt 1883 (Box 811, Folder 3)
  - University of Leipzig "Biblische Theologie des Alten Testaments" with Dr. Franz Delitzsch 1883 (Box 811, Folder 4)
  - University of Gottingen, "Humes Philosophie" with G.E. Müller 1882 (Box 811, Folder 5)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - A-B, misc. 1904 - 1921 (Box 812, Folder 1)
  - Branch, Anna Hempstead (Class of 1897) 1897 - 1924 (Box 812, Folder 2)
  - C, misc. 1993 - 1925 (Box 812, Folder 3)
  - Cable, George Washington 1891 - 1921 (Box 812, Folder 4)
  - E-F, misc. 1897 - 1927 (Box 812, Folder 5)
  - Eckstrom, Fanny Hardy (Class of 1888) 1900 - 1909 (Box 812, Folder 6)
  - Edwards, Anna undated (Box 812, Folder 7)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 1906 - 1909 (Box 812, Folder 8)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 10/1909 - 12/1909 (Box 812, Folder 9)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 01/1910 - 03/1910 (Box 812, Folder 10)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 04/1910 - 05/1910 (Box 812, Folder 11)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 06/1910 - 11/1912 (Box 812, Folder 12)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 01/1913 - 03/1913 (Box 812, Folder 13)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 04/1913 - 12/1913 (Box 812, Folder 14)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 1914 (Box 812, Folder 15)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 01/1915 - 06/1915 (Box 812, Folder 16)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 01/1916 - 05/1921 (Box 812, Folder 17)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 10/1926 - 12/1926 (Box 812, Folder 18)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 01/1927 - 05/1927 (Box 812, Folder 19)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 08/1927 - 10/1927 (Box 812, Folder 20)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche (Class of 1912) 11/1927 - 12/1927 (Box 812, Folder 21)
  - Edwards, Norman 1914 - 1917 (Box 812, Folder 22)
  - Edwards, Walter J. 1914 - 1927 (Box 812, Folder 23)
  - G-H, misc. 1894 - 1926 (Box 812, Folder 24)
  - Goutroux, Ernst 1897 - 1901 (Box 812, Folder 25)
  - J-R, misc. 1895 - 1910 (Box 812, Folder 26)
  - Jackson, Florence (Class of 1893) 1897 - 1925 (Box 812, Folder 27)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers 1906 - 1918 (Box 812, Folder 28)
  - Price, Evelyn (Class of 1924) 1923 (Box 812, Folder 29)
  - S-Z, misc. 1892 - 1927 (Box 812, Folder 30)
  - Seelye, Laurenus Clarke 1884 (Box 812, Folder 31)
  - Taylor, Alfred Edwards 1904 (Box 812, Folder 32)
  - Ward, James 1909 - 1910 (Box 812, Folder 33)
  - Philosophers Correspondence Scrapbook see below (Box 813, Folder 1)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - A, misc 1892 - 1901 (Box 813, Folder 2)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - B, misc 1894 - 1920 (Box 813, Folder 3)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - C, misc 1894 - 1902 (Box 813, Folder 4)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - D, misc 1883 - 1915 (Box 813, Folder 5)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Dana, Charles L. 1895 - 1910 (Box 813, Folder 6)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - F-G, misc 1907 - 1909 (Box 813, Folder 7)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Gildersleeve, Basil L. 1904 (Box 813, Folder 8)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Hadley, Arthur Twining 1904 - 1906 (Box 813, Folder 9)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Hibbert Journal 1908 - 1919 (Box 813, Folder 10)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Hirn, Yrjo 1900 - 1901 (Box 813, Folder 11)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Hoernlé, R.F. Alfred 1914 - 1916 (Box 813, Folder 12)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - James, William 1891 - 1901 (Box 813, Folder 13)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Jastrow, Joseph 1901 (Box 813, Folder 14)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Joachim, Harold H. 1912 - 1914 (Box 813, Folder 15)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - L-M, misc 1905 - 1919 (Box 813, Folder 16)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - McDougall, William 1919 - 1923 (Box 813, Folder 17)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Miller, Dickinson S. 1899 - 1917 (Box 813, Folder 18)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - More, Paul Elmer 1911 - 1916 (Box 813, Folder 19)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Morgan, Conway Lloyd 1894 - 1900 (Box 813, Folder 20)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Myers, Charles Samuel 1907 - 1920 (Box 813, Folder 21)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - P, misc 1895 - 1913 (Box 813, Folder 22)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Robinson, G. Croom 1888 - 1891 (Box 813, Folder 23)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Royce, Josiah 1890 - 1916 (Box 813, Folder 24)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - S-T, misc 1896 - 1919 (Box 813, Folder 25)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Schiller, D. Canning Scott 1901 - 1922 (Box 813, Folder 26)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Charles Scribners Sons 1919 (Box 813, Folder 27)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Shand, Alexander F. 1914 - 1915 (Box 813, Folder 28)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Sheldon, Wilmon H. 1923 - 1924 (Box 813, Folder 29)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Stout, George F. 1894 - 1907 (Box 813, Folder 30)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - W, misc 1919 - 1927 (Box 813, Folder 31)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Ward, James A. 1899 - 1910 (Box 813, Folder 32)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - Watson, John Broadus 1914 (Box 813, Folder 33)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers - unidentified 1891 - 1925 (Box 813, Folder 34)
- SERIES III. LECTURE NOTES
  - Class Roll Book (includes grades) 1906 - 1909 (Box 814, Folder 1)
  - miscellaneous 1925, undated (Box 814, Folder 2)
  - exams and paper topics 1897 - 1924 (Box 814, Folder 3)
  - Bosanquet's Principles of Individuality and Value 1916 (Box 814, Folder 4)
  - History of Greek Philosophy 1892 - 1910 (Box 814, Folder 5)
  - History of Philosophy, "syllabi and paper topics" 1911 - 1919 (Box 814, Folder 6)
  - History of Philosophy, "introduction" 1892 - 1923 (Box 814, Folder 7)
  - History of Philosophy, "Bacon and Hobbes" undated (Box 814, Folder 8)
  - History of Philosophy, "Berkeley" undated (Box 814, Folder 9)
  - History of Philosophy, "Descartes" undated (Box 814, Folder 10)
  - History of Philosophy, "Fichte" 1899 (Box 814, Folder 11)
  - History of Philosophy, "Hegel" undated (Box 814, Folder 12)
  - History of Philosophy, "Kant" undated (Box 814, Folder 13)
  - History of Philosophy, "Leibniz" undated (Box 814, Folder 14)
  - History of Philosophy, "Locke" undated (Box 814, Folder 15)
  - History of Philosophy, "Nicolas of Kues" undated (Box 814, Folder 16)
  - History of Philosophy, "Schopenhauer" undated (Box 814, Folder 17)
  - History of Philosophy, "Spencer" undated (Box 814, Folder 18)
  - History of Philosophy, "Spinoza" undated (Box 814, Folder 19)
  - History of Philosophy, "misc. notes I" 1884, undated (Box 814, Folder 20)
  - History of Philosophy, "misc. notes II" 1900, undated (Box 814, Folder 21)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, "outline" undated (Box 815, Folder 1)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, "Introduction" 1897 (Box 815, Folder 2)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, "Divisions of Philosophy" undated (Box 815, Folder 3)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, "Logic" undated (Box 815, Folder 4)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, "Problems of Knowledge" undated (Box 815, Folder 5)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, "Critical Comments on the Conflicts of Epistemology" undated (Box 815, Folder 6)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, "Metaphysics, gen" undated (Box 815, Folder 7)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, "Metaphysics, The Philosophy of Nature and the Philosophy of the Mind" undated (Box 815, Folder 8)
  - Logic I undated (Box 815, Folder 9)
  - Logic II undated (Box 815, Folder 10)
  - Metaphysics 1907 - 1908 (Box 815, Folder 11)
  - Metaphysics undated (Box 815, Folder 12)
  - Metaphysics, "The Composition of Aristotle's Metaphysics" undated (Box 815, Folder 13)
  - Mysticism, "Introduction" undated (Box 816, Folder 1)
  - Mysticism, "Pietistic Mysticism of Bernard of Clairvance" undated (Box 816, Folder 2)
  - Nature, Method and Scope of Psychology undated (Box 816, Folder 3)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Typescript" 1923 (Box 816, Folder 4)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Introduction" undated (Box 816, Folder 5)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "The Aims and Methods of Christian Life" undated (Box 816, Folder 6)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Biblical Doctrine of the Trinity" undated (Box 816, Folder 7)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Doctrine of Sin" undated (Box 816, Folder 8)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Euken on 'The Truth of Religion'" undated (Box 816, Folder 9)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Naturalism and Agnosticism" undated (Box 816, Folder 10)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Philosophy and Faith" 1891 (Box 816, Folder 11)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "The Solitude of Christ" undated (Box 816, Folder 12)
  - Philosophy of Religion,"Theology of St. Paul" undated (Box 816, Folder 13)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Value of the Study of the History of Religion" undated (Box 816, Folder 14)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "miscellaneous" undated (Box 816, Folder 15)
  - Philosophy of Religion, "Notebooks I and II" undated (Box 816, Folder 16)
  - Plotinus undated (Box 816, Folder 17)
- SERIES IV. NOTES
  - Notes, Misc. I 1927 - 1928 (Box 817, Folder 1)
  - Notes, Misc. II undated (Box 817, Folder 2)
  - Bowne, "Metaphysics" 1882 (Box 817, Folder 3)
  - Bromse, "Die Realitat du Zeit" 1889 (Box 817, Folder 4)
  - Color Theories and Color blindness undated (Box 817, Folder 5)
  - Deuteronomy I undated (Box 817, Folder 6)
  - Deuteronomy II undated (Box 817, Folder 7)
  - Fichte, Hegel, Gebart, Ladd, Lotze undated (Box 817, Folder 8)
  - The Future of the People of European Turkey 1885 (Box 817, Folder 9)
  - Ideation and Intellection undated (Box 817, Folder 10)
  - Marshall, Henry Rutgers, Aesthetics, Chaps. XIII-XVI undated (Box 817, Folder 11)
  - Time undated (Box 817, Folder 12)
  - Sartor Resartus by Thomas Carlyle 1896 (Box 818, Folder 1)
  - Bagster's Critical New Testament undated (Box 818, Folder 2)
- SERIES V. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - photographs 1885 - 1898 (Box 819, Folder 1)
  - photographs 1898 - 1924 (Box 819, Folder 2)
  - photographs, "In Classroom" 1889 (Box 819, Folder 3)
  - photographs, "Snapshots" 1884 - 1927 (Box 819, Folder 4)
  - photographs, "by Katherine McClellan" 1901 (Box 819, Folder 5)
  - photographs, "by Eric Stahlberg" undated (Box 819, Folder 6)
  - portrait 1915 (Box 819, Folder 7)
- SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS
  - "The First 25 Years of the American Philosophical Association", Philosophical Review 1925 (Box 820, Folder 1)
  - "History of Modern Philosophy in the Formative Period from the Renaissance to Kant", Outlines of Modern Philosophy 1892 (Box 820, Folder 2)
  - "Jonathan Edwards: an Appreciation" undated (Box 820, Folder 3)
  - "Meister Eckhardt the Mystic", Journal of Speculative Philosophy (Box 820, Folder 4)
  - "The Psychology of the Affections in Plato and Aristotle", Philosophical Review 1919 (Box 820, Folder 5)
  - Reviews by Gardiner 1906 (Box 820, Folder 6)
  - Selected Sermons of Jonathan Edwards 1903 - 1904 (Box 820, Folder 7)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1924 - 1925 (Box 820, Folder 8)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1924 (Box 820, Folder 9)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1925 (Box 820, Folder 10)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1924 (Box 820, Folder 11)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1905 - 1927 (Box 820, Folder 12)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1924 (Box 820, Folder 13)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1924 - 1926 (Box 820, Folder 14)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1888 - 1925 (Box 820, Folder 15)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1924 (Box 820, Folder 16)
  - A History of Smith College, notes 1925 - 1927 (Box 820, Folder 17)
  - A History of Smith College, "Curriculum" undated (Box 820, Folder 18)
  - A History of Smith College, "Course of Study" 1924 (Box 820, Folder 19)
  - A History of Smith College, "Course of Study" undated (Box 820, Folder 20)
  - A History of Smith College, "Baldwin, Ruth Bowles" 1887 (Box 820, Folder 21)
  - A History of Smith College, "Cone, Kate Morris" 1879 (Box 820, Folder 22)
  - A History of Smith College, "Cutler, Anna Alice" 1885 (Box 820, Folder 23)
  - A History of Smith College, "Daskam, Josephine D." 1898 (Box 820, Folder 24)
  - A History of Smith College, "Fuller, Caroline M." 1895 (Box 820, Folder 25)
  - A History of Smith College, "Fuller, Mary Breese" 1894 (Box 820, Folder 26)
  - A History of Smith College, "Greene, Helen French" 1891 (Box 820, Folder 27)
  - A History of Smith College, "Gulliver, Mary" 1882 (Box 820, Folder 28)
  - A History of Smith College, "Hall, Edith Hayward" 1899 (Box 820, Folder 29)
  - A History of Smith College, "Huntington, Eliza P." 1881 (Box 820, Folder 30)
  - A History of Smith College, "Mansfield, Margery S." 1917 (Box 820, Folder 31)
  - A History of Smith College, "Palmer, Harriet W." 1879 (Box 820, Folder 32)
  - A History of Smith College, "Peloubet, Mary Alice" 1882 (Box 820, Folder 33)
  - A History of Smith College, "Russell, Annie Maria" 1886 (Box 820, Folder 34)
  - A History of Smith College, "Seaver, Florence W." 1889 (Box 820, Folder 35)
  - A History of Smith College, "Wilder, Harris Hawthorne" 1924 (Box 820, Folder 36)
  - A History of Smith College, "Woods, Eleanor Bush" 1896 (Box 820, Folder 37)
  - typescript, Aristotle: parva naturalia undated (Box 821, Folder 1)
  - "Introduction", manuscript undated (Box 821, Folder 2)
  - "Introduction", typescript undated (Box 821, Folder 3)
  - "Of Sense and Its Objects", manuscript undated (Box 821, Folder 4)
  - "Of Sense and Its Objects", typescript undated (Box 821, Folder 5)
  - "Of Sense and Its Objects", notes undated (Box 821, Folder 6)
  - "Of Memory and Reminiscences", manuscript and typescript undated (Box 821, Folder 7)
  - "Of Sleep and Waking…", manuscript undated (Box 821, Folder 8)
  - "Of Sleep and Waking…", typescript undated (Box 821, Folder 9)
  - "Of Long and Short Life", typescript undated (Box 821, Folder 10)
  - "Of Youth and Old Age", manuscript undated (Box 821, Folder 12)
  - "Of Youth and Old Age", typescript undated (Box 821, Folder 13)
  - "bibliography", manuscript and typescript undated (Box 821, Folder 14)
  - miscellaneous, notes I 1891, undated (Box 821, Folder 15)
  - miscellaneous, notes II undated (Box 821, Folder 16)
  - miscellaneous, notes III undated (Box 821, Folder 17)
  - miscellaneous, notes IV undated (Box 821, Folder 18)
  - miscellaneous, notes V undated (Box 821, Folder 19)
  - miscellaneous, notes VI undated (Box 821, Folder 20)
  - miscellaneous, notes VII undated (Box 821, Folder 21)
  - miscellaneous, notes VIII undated (Box 821, Folder 22)
  - A History of the Theories of Feeling and Emotion Before the Nineteenth Century, "Table of Contents" undated (Box 822, Folder 1)
  - Introductory Note undated (Box 822, Folder 2)
  - "The Beginning of a Doctrine of Affections: From Heraclitus to Plato" undated (Box 822, Folder 3)
  - The Doctrine of Pleasure, Pain, and Emotion in Aristotle undated (Box 822, Folder 4)
  - "Ancient Theories of the Affections" undated (Box 822, Folder 5)
  - "Patristic and Medieval Doctrines of the Affections" undated (Box 822, Folder 6)
  - "Affective Psychology in the Period of the Renaissance" undated (Box 822, Folder 7)
  - "Systems of 'Passions' in the 17th Century: Descartes and Malebranche" undated (Box 822, Folder 8)
  - "Systems of 'Passions' in the 17th Century: Hobbes and Spinoza" undated (Box 822, Folder 9)
  - "Affective Psychology of the 18th Century: British Moralists and Associationists" undated (Box 822, Folder 10)
  - "Affective Psychology of the 18th Century: French and German" undated (Box 822, Folder 11)
  - Bibliography undated (Box 822, Folder 12)
  - A History of the Theories of Feeling and Emotion Before the Nineteenth Century, notebooks undated (Box 823)
  - A History of the Theories of Feeling and Emotion Before the Nineteenth Century, notebooks undated (Box 824)
  - manuscript notebooks 1916 - 1917 (Box 824.1, Folder 1)
  - manuscript notebooks 1916 - 1917 (Box 824.1, Folder 2)
  - manuscript notebooks 1916 - 1917 (Box 824.1, Folder 3)
  - manuscript notebooks 1916 - 1917 (Box 824.1, Folder 4)
  - manuscript notebooks 1916 - 1917 (Box 824.1, Folder 5)
  - Chapters I-III, manuscript undated (Box 824.1, Folder 6)
  - Chapter IV, manuscript undated (Box 824.1, Folder 7)